Joseph Priestley Papers 1771-1803 Mss.B.P931 Mss.B.P931
American Philosophical Society
Joseph Priestley Papers
1771-1803
Mss.B.P931
American Philosophical Society
0.5 Linear feet
Correspondence of Joseph Priestley, scientist, Unitarian minister, and republican theorist. The collection includes 41 letters written to John Vaughan, 1791-1800, 5 letters to other correspondents, and manuscripts and photostats of 68 items in the Municipal Library, Warrington, England, on theological issues, the internal development of the United States, the French Revolution and its aftermath, Unitarianism, science, his publications, and American Philosophical Society.
Priestley, Joseph, 1733-1804
Early American History Note
The Joseph Priestley Collection contains a series of original letters (about 40) from this leading scientist and thinker. The letters date to the 1790s. The MOLE entry contains a detailed inventory of the original letters. There is also a box of photostats in a separate box.
Related Archival Materials note
Priestley appears as a correspondent or is mentioned in several other collections at the American Philosophical Society, including in the Benjamin Franklin Papers (eight letters from Johannes Ingenhousz to Franklin, 1774-1782); the John Pershouse Papers (four from John Pershouse to James Pershouse, 1802-1805), and the Richard Price Papers (four from Richard Price to Charles Chauncy and Benjamin Franklin, 1766-1779).
A manuscript copy of Priestley's "Experiments relating to phlogiston and the conversion of water into air," 1783 (32 pp.), is housed separately at 540.1 P931.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Photostats from the Municipal Library, Warrington, England, courtesy of the Library through Whitfield J. Bell, 1951.
Scope and Contents note
The Joseph Priestley Papers consists of 46 letters and 70 copies of letters written by the scientist, educator, and Unitarian minister, Joseph Priestley, mostly to the Librarian of the American Philosophical Society, John Vaughan, and Priestley's brother-in-law, John Wilkinson. The focus in these letters is at once personal and intellectual, providing insight into Priestley's financial life, the vicissitudes of his work and political and religious ideas.
The several letters written by Priestley to Vaughan in the years between the Birmingham riots and his emigration to America provide valuable insight into a variety of personal and financial matters (Vaughan held power of attorney for him), cloaked, of course, in the violence of the anti-Republican backlash. Priestley's difficult decision to send first his sons, then himself abroad due to the "increasing bigotry and violence of the High church party" in England are thoroughly chronicled, as are his bitterness against the confluence of "church power," xenophobia, and anti-Republicanism.
Although Priestley's post-emigration letters from Northumberland tend to be more perfunctory, relating primarily to business matters, they provide a useful perspective on his intellectual isolation and on the toll that decades of political controversy had taken upon the man. His dismay at anti-tax hysteria in western Pennsylvania during the Whiskey Rebellion is evident in his lament that "People will chuse to do without government rather than pay so dear for it, and if they really chuse this, they should be left to themselves." Other letters reveal Priestley's frustration at his inability to obtain decent scientific instruments in America - and implicitly, the inability to advance his own research agenda -- and his publications continue to make their mark, particularly in his uneven relationship with the Porcupine, William Cobbett.
The balance of the collection consists of an additional five letters of Priestley, including a fine letter to Dr. [William] Withering (1741-1799), October 27, 1795, discussing Priestley's nostalgia for the comradery of the Lunar Society, his on-going chemical experiments with phlogisticated air, and much more. There are also photostats of 68 letters to and from Priestley's brother-in-law, John Wilkinson (1789-1802), drawn from originals held in the Municipal Library, Warrington, England. These provide particularly valuable insight into Priestley's personal response to the Birmingham riots, and his reactions to the isolated life in Northumberland, and they contain important commentary on Priestley's religious, political, and scientific views from the 1790s until 1802.
Biographical/Historical note
As scientist, Unitarian controversialist, and proponent of republican values, Joseph Priestley exerted enormous influence in English and American intellectual circles, though his life ended in decline and isolation. Born into middling circumstances in Yorkshire, Priestley was raised by well to do relatives who had fallen under the sway of dissenting doctrine. A promising student, he prepared for the ministry, but as a result of ill health and his unpalatable religious affiliations he was prevented from entering either Oxford or Cambridge, choosing instead to attend the dissenting academy at Daventry.
Receiving his degree in 1755, Priestley discovered that his road into the ministry was hampered by his unorthodox views and unfortunate voice, and while filling a minor pulpit, he found that his first real taste of success came instead in teaching. By 1761, his reputation as an educator had grown to such an extent that he was offered the position of Professor of Languages at the prestigious Warrington Academy, and the next year his life improved further when he was ordained and married Mary Wilkinson, daughter of a Welsh ironmaster. In education as in religion, Priestley's approach was insistently unorthodox. He introduced the study of modern history, law, economics, and social sciences into the standard curriculum, and although he left Warrington in 1767 to return to the more stable income of the ministry, accepting an appointment in Leeds, his reputation as a scholar and scientist had grown enormously. At Leeds, he became acquainted with Benjamin Franklin who encouraged his electrical experimentation, and Priestley's work on light and vision found a wide readership.
By 1773, Priestley had attracted the attention of William Petty, 1st Earl of Shelburne (1737-1805), and was offered a position in the Earl's household as tutor, librarian, and companion. The grandson of the great scientist of the same name, Shelburne was a prominent politician, a future Prime Minister, and a magnanimous patron. Through him, Priestley not only achieved financial security, but gained entrée into the highest of Britain's intellectual, social, and scientific circles. At Bowood, Shelburne's estate, Priestley pursued the implications of a paper he had presented to the Royal Society in 1772, "On Different Kinds of Air," and thus laid the foundation of his international reputation as a chemist. In his book, Experiments and Observations on Different Kinds of Air (1774), he built upon the work of Joseph Black and James Cavendish to identify nine distinct gases, three of which were previously unknown. Most famously, on August 1, 1774, he produced "dephlogisticated air" - oxygen -- by heating red mercuric oxide, demonstrating beyond cavil that air was not an element. In isolating oxygen, Priestley noted its importance in combustion, but clung to a belief in phlogistic theory until the end of his life, becoming, at the end, the last important chemist of that stripe. Ironically, it was his isolation of oxygen, particularly as pursued by Antoine Lavoisier, that became the nail in the phlogistic coffin. His scientific work earned Priestley admission into the French Academy of Sciences in 1772, the St. Petersburg Academy in 1780, and through Franklin, to the American Philosophical Society in 1784.
During the later 1770s, divisions between Priestley and Shelburne deteriorated over Priestley's support for the American cause during the Revolution and over his unorthodox religious views. While the two remained cordial, Priestley left the Shelburne home in 1780 and settled at Birmingham, near his brother-in-law, John Wilkinson. Whereas his scientific work had flourished at Bowood, his religious writings flourished in Birmingham, and he became a leading dissenting voice, assailing the corruptions of the Anglican hierarchy and Trinitarianism, and beginning the enduring association with Unitarianism that he considered his true life's work. At Birmingham he was also drawn into the Lunar Society, an engaging, salon-like group of enlightened minds that included Erasmus Darwin, James Watt, and Matthew Boulton.
The halcyon days in Birmingham, however, were not to last. Priestley's religious and political views conspired to ensure his supreme unpopularity during the shifting political tides of the French Revolutionary era, and he became a lightning rod for the government-inspired backlash against republicanism and "radicalism" of all sorts. The wrath of the mob was turned against him directly during the Birmingham riots of July, 1791, when his house, library, and laboratory were set aflame. Taking refuge with William Vaughan, brother of John and Benjamin, Priestley whisked his children out of the country and in April, 1794, finally abandoned England himself for the United States.
Priestley and his wife, Mary, settled in the relatively remote town of Northumberland, Pennsylvania, 150 miles west of Philadelphia, initially imaging that he could enjoy the country life and yet travel into the metropolis for intellectual stimulation. Little, however, went as Priestley had planned. His plans of establishing a community at Northumberland devoted to religious and political freedom were unavailing, travel into Philadelphia proved far too difficult, and in his rural remove he was only barely able to continue his scientific research. If it cannot be traced to Birmingham, Priestley's protracted decline began in 1795 and 1796 when he lost his son and wife successively, and thereafter he was never in complete health himself. Furthermore, Priestley was no more immune in the United States than he had been in England to ill political winds. When his friend, Thomas Cooper, was arrested for violating the Alien and Sedition Acts, Priestley was suspected of aiding and abetting, and although his deportation was prevented by the intervention of his friend John Adams, he became a preferred target for the literary quills of Peter Porcupine, William Cobbett. Although Priestley continued to serve in the Unitarian pulpit and wrote on religious matters for several years more, his last scientific work (on the long-abandonded phlogiston) was published in 1796. He died after a brief illness on February 6, 1804, and is buried in the Quaker cemetery in Northumberland.
Belsham, Thomas, 1750-1829; Cardale, Paul; Lindsey, Theophilus; Mansell, Judith; Vaughan, John, 1756-1841; Wilkinson, John, 1789-1802; Withering, William, 1741-1799; American Philosophical Society; Business Records and Accounts; Chemistry--18th century; Church and State--Great Britain--18th century; Cobbett, William, 1763-1835; Early National Politics; France--History--Revolution, 1789-1799; Great Britain--Politics and government--1789-1820; Legal Records; Oxygen; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809; Phlogiston; Riots--England--Birmingham; Science and technology; Scientific Correspondence; Taxation; Vaughan, Benjamin, 1751-1835
- Papers
  - Letter to [William Eden, first baron Auckland], Dec. 18, 1771; 9x7-1/2; Priestley, Joseph, 1733-1804
    Scope and Contents note
    Leeds, A.L.S. 2p. (see Priestley papers.) Concerning the appointments made to accompany Cook on his voyages. Refers to Banks.
  - Letter to the Rev. Mr. [Paul] Cardale, March 23, 1774; 7 3/4" x 12 3/4"; Priestley, Joseph, 1733-1804
    London, A.L.S. 1p. and add. (see his Letters to various persons,no.42) Relative to the [Theological] Repository.
  - Letter to ---- ----, July 24, 1780; 7 1/4" x 9"; Priestley, Joseph, 1733-1804
    Calne, A.L.S. 3p. (see his Letters to various persons,no.43) Relative to the loan of certain books.
  - Letter to the Rev. Mr. [Thomas] Belsham, April 27, 1789; 7 3/4" x 12 1/2"; Priestley, Joseph, 1733-1804
    London... A.L.S. 3p. and add. (see his Letters to various persons,no.44) Urges Mr. Belsham to accept position at the Academy at Hackney. Proposed new translation of the Bible. Contain fine impression of seal.
  - Letter to the Rev. Mr. [Thomas] Belsham, May 4, 1789; 7 1/4" x 9 1/2"; Priestley, Joseph, 1733-1804
    Birmingham, A.L.S. 3p. and add. (see his Letters to various persons,no.45) Relative to his decision to accept the place at Hackney. Proposed new translation of the Bible. Contains seal.
  - Letter to the members of the New Meeting Congregation of Birmingham, Oct. 8, 1791; 10" x 16"; Priestley, Joseph, 1733-1804
    London, Copy of L. 2p. (see his Letters to various persons,no.46) Declines invitation to return to Birmingham to resume his pastorate.
  - Letter to John Vaughan, Oct. 22, 1791; 7 1/2" x 10"; Priestley, Joseph, 1733-1804
    London, A.L.S. 3p. and add. (see his Letters to John Vaughan, No.1) Finances. Progress of Unitarianism in America. Has some prospect of settling at Hackney as successor to Dr. Price.
  - Letter to John Vaughan, Nov. 15, 1791; 7 3/4" x 10"; Priestley, Joseph, 1733-1804
    London, A.L.S. 3p. and add. (see this Letters to John Vaughan, no.2) Finances. Birmingham riots. About to publish Appeal to the public.
  - Letter to [John Vaughan], Dec. 7, 1791; 7 3/4" x 10"; Priestley, Joseph, 1733-1804
    London, A.L.S. 2p. (see his Letters to John Vaughan, no.3) Finances. Has begun his ministry at Hackney.
  - Letter to Miss J[udith] Mansell, Dec. 27, 1791; 8" x 9 3/4"; Priestley, Joseph, 1733-1804
    Clapton, A.L.S. 2p. (see his Letters to various persons,no.47) Glad his picture was acceptable. Household articles he would like sent to him.
  - Letter to John Vaughan, Feb. 27, 1792; 7 3/4" x 10"; Priestley, Joseph, 1733-1804
    London, A.L.S. 3p. and add. (see his Letters to John Vaughan, no.4) Finances. Possibility of his settling in America.
  - Letter to John Vaughan, June 7, 1792; 7 3/4" x 10"; Priestley, Joseph, 1733-1804
    Clapton, A.L.S. 3p. and add. (see his Letters to John Vaughan,no.5) Finances. Acknowledges Mr. Vaughan's offer to take one of his sons under his wing in America. Politics of England in an unquiet state. French revolution.
  - Letter to John Vaughan, Feb. 6, 1793; 7 3/4" x 10"; Priestley, Joseph, 1733-1804
    Clapton, A.L.S. 3p. and add. (see his Letters to John Vaughan,no.6) His sons are forced to leave England because of the biogtry and violence of the church party. About 100 families are thinking of settling in Kentucky. He will go to either France or America.
  - Letter to the Rev. Mr. [Theophilus] Lindsey, April 9, 1794; 6 1/4" x 8"; Priestley, Joseph, 1733-1804
    Off Deal, A.L.S. 3p. and add. (see his letters to various persons,no.48) His departure from England [for America].
  - Letter to John Vaughan, June 3, 1794; 6 1/2" x 8"; Priestley, Joseph, 1733-1804
    Sandy Hook, A.L.S. 2p., add. and end. (see his Letters to John Vaughan,no.7) He and his wife have just arrived at Sandy Hook.
  - Letter to John Vaughan, Aug. 1, 1794; 8" x 13"; Priestley, Joseph, 1733-1804
    Northumberland, A.L.S. 3p. and add. (see his letters to John Vaughan, no.8) Doubts whether he will have occasion for a house in Philadelphia. Desires to lay a foundation for a Unitarian society. Promotion of science. Opposition to government by the western settlers because of the excise.
  - Letter to John Vaughan, Aug. 16, 1794; 8" x 13"; Priestley, Joseph, 1733-1804
    Northumberland, A.L.S. 1p., add. and end. (see his Letters to John Vaughan,no.9) Plans to settle in Northumberland rather than in Philadelphia.
  - Letter to John Vaughan, Aug. 30, 1794; 6 1/2" x 8"; Priestley, Joseph, 1733-1804
    Northumberland, A.L.S. 1p., add. and end. (see his Letters to John Vaughan,no.10) Finances. Plans for building a house.
  - Letter to John Vaughan, Sept. 17, 1794; 8" x 13"; Priestley, Joseph, 1733-1804
    Northumberland, A.L.S. 1p. and add. (see his Letters to John Vaughan, no.11) Finances. Enclosures for England.
  - Letter to John Vaughan, Nov. 13, 1794; 8" x 13"; Priestley, Joseph, 1733-1804
    Northumberland, A.L.S. 1p. and add. (see his Letters to John Vaughan, no.12) Finances. Enclosures for England. Mentions Mr. [Thomas?] Cooper.
  - Letter to [John Vaughan], Nov. 17, 1794; 6 1/2" x 8"; Priestley, Joseph, 1733-1804
    Northumberland, A.L.S. 1p. and end. (see his Letters to John Vaughan,no.13) Finances.
  - Letter to Mr. [ ] Mckinney, Nov. 21, 1794; 6 1/2" x 8"; Priestley, Joseph, 1733-1804
    Northumberland, A.L.S. 3p. and add. (see his Letters to various persons,no.49) Household articles being sent to him. Mentions [John] Vaughan.
  - Letter to John Vaughan, Dec. 10, 1794; 6 1/2" x 8"; Priestley, Joseph, 1733-1804
    Northumberland, A.L.S. 1p. and add. (see his Letters to John Vaughan,no.14) Received cider and apples. Pays bill.
  - Letter to John Vaughan, Dec. 12, 1794; 6 1/2" x 8"; Priestley, Joseph, 1733-1804
    Northumberland, A.L.S. 4p. (see his Letters to John Vaughan, no.15) Missing furniture. Arrival of Mr. Cooper. The new house.
  - Letter to John Vaughan, Dec. 16, 1794; 6 1/2" x 8"; Priestley, Joseph, 1733-1804
    Northumberland, A.L.S. 1p., add. and end. (see his Letters to John Vaughan,no.16) Finances. Still no information about the missing furniture.
  - Letter to John Vaughan, Dec. 21, 1794; 8" x 13"; Priestley, Joseph, 1733-1804
    Northumberland, A.L.S. 1p. and add. (see his Letters to John Vaughan,no.17) Mentions Mr. Cooper. Supplies for his experiments.
  - Letter to John Vaughan, Jan. 4, 1795; 8" x 10"; Priestley, Joseph, 1733-1804
    Northumberland, A.L.S. 3p. and add. (see his Letters to John Vaughan,no.18) Missing household articles. Proposed college of Northumberland. Mentions Mr. Cooper and Mr. [Harry] Toulmin]. Advance in postage rates. Reproduced and printed in part: APS Library Bulletin for 1946,p.80.
  - Power of attorney to John Vaughan, Feb. 17, 1795; 12-3/4x8; Priestley, Joseph, 1733-1804
    D.S.: Joseph Priestley. Witnessed: Jonathan Walker and W[illia]m Cook. Certified: Wm.Cook. 1p.and end. (see Joseph Priestley Papers.)
  - Letter to John Vaughan, Feb. 22, 1795; 8" x 13"; Priestley, Joseph, 1733-1804
    Northumberland, A.L.S. 1p. and add. (see his Letters to John Vaughan,no.19) The purchase of a lot in Northumberland.
  - Letter to John Vaughan, May 4, 1795; 6 1/2" x 8"; Priestley, Joseph, 1733-1804
    Northumberland, A.L.S. 1p., add. and end. (see his Letters to John Vaughan,no.20) Finances.
  - Letter to John Vaughan, May 6, 1795; 8" x 13"; Priestley, Joseph, 1733-1804
    Northumberland, A.L.S. 2p. and add. (see his Letters to John Vaughan,no.21) Finances. Possibility of Benjamin Vaughan's settling in Boston. Wishes to deliver a series of discourses on the evidences of Christianity; asks that he question his friends on the subject, mentioning particularly Dr. Rush.
  - Letter to John Vaughan, June 4, 1795; 6 1/2" x 8"; Priestley, Joseph, 1733-1804
    Northumberland, A.L.S. 2p. and add. (see his Letters to John Vaughan,no.22) Parcels from London. Finances. Proposed visit to Philadelphia.
  - Letter to John Vaughan, June 15, 1795; 6 1/2" x 8"; Priestley, Joseph, 1733-1804
    Northumberland, A.L.S. 1p., add. and end. (see his Letters to John Vaughan,no.23) Finances. Proposed visit to Philadelphia.
  - Letter to John Vaughan, Aug. 11, 1795; 8" x 13"; Priestley, Joseph, 1733-1804
    Northumberland, A.L.S. 2p. and add. (see his Letters to John Vaughan,no.24) One of his pamphlets in press; difficulty in getting his tracts to England; his Answer to Mr. Paine. Finances. The college
  - Letter to John Vaughan, Aug. 13, 1795; 8" x 13"; Priestley, Joseph, 1733-1804
    Northumberland, A.L.S. 1p. and add. (see his Letters to John Vaughan,no.25) More letters and pamphlets for England. Finances.
  - Letter to John Vaughan, Aug. 31, 1795; 8" x 10"; Priestley, Joseph, 1733-1804
    Northumberland, A.L.S. 2p. and add. (see his Letters to John Vaughan,no.26) Finances. Building of his house. The settlement of his sons.
  - Letter to Dr. [William] Withering, Birmingham, Eng., Oct. 27, 1795; 13" x 8"; Priestley, Joseph, 1733-1804
    Northumberland co., A.L.S. 3p. and add., end. Study of the phlogistication of air. Appointed principal of the College of Northumberland. Mentions Lunar society; APS publications.
  - Letter to John Vaughan, Oct. 28, 1795; 6 1/2" x 8"; Priestley, Joseph, 1733-1804
    Northumberland, A.L.S. 3p. and add. (see his Letters to John Vaughan,no.27) Finances. Inquires about Benjamin Vaughan. Ill health of Mrs. Priestley. An anonymous letter recently received.
  - Letter to John Vaughan, Feb. 3, 1796; 6 1/2" x 8"; Priestley, Joseph, 1733-1804
    Northumberland, A.L.S. 2p. and add. (see his Letters to John Vaughan,no.28) Delivery of certain parcels. Has prepared a set of discourses. Mentions Mr. Cooper.
  - Letter to John Vaughan, May 30, 1796; 8" x 13"; Priestley, Joseph, 1733-1804
    Northumberland, A.L.S. 1p., add. and end. (see his Letters to John Vaughan,no.29) Dr. Barton lent him copy of Bancroft's book on color; expects to try some experiments. Family news.
  - Letter to [Benjamin Smith] Barton, Philadelphia, June 16, 1796; 8x6-1/4; Priestley, Joseph, 1733-1804
    Northumberland, Photo.of A.L.S. 3p.and add.,end. (see Priestley papers.) Concerning his publication on phlogiston. Botany. Asks for his article on Indian artifacts. Refers to J.Vaughan. From original in Central Library, Salford, England.
    Not Found: 3/2011
  - Letter to John Vaughan, July 28, 1796; 8" x 13"; Priestley, Joseph, 1733-1804
    Northumberland, A.L.S. 1p., add. and end. (see his Letters to John Vaughan,no.30) Scientific instruments.
  - Letter to John Vaughan, Aug. 18, 1796; 8" x 13"; Priestley, Joseph, 1733-1804
    Northumberland, A.L.S. 1p., add. and end. (see his Letters to John Vaughan,no.31) Finances. Packages.
  - Letter to John Vaughan, Sept. 22, 1796; 8" x 13"; Priestley, Joseph, 1733-1804
    Northumberland, A.L.S. 1p. and add. (see his Letters to John Vaughan,no.32) Sends last thing his wife wrote; her fondness for the Vaughan family.
  - Letter to John Vaughan, Oct. 29, 1796; 8 1/2" x 13"; Priestley, Joseph, 1733-1804
    Northumberland, A.L.S. 1p. and add. (see his Letters to John Vaughan,no.33) Letters to be forwarded. His son.
  - Letter to John Vaughan, Nov. 3, 1796; 8" x 13"; Priestley, Joseph, 1733-1804
    Northumberland, A.L.S. 1p. and add. Mutilated (see his Letters to John Vaughan,no.34) Finances.
  - Letter to Miss Judith Mansell, Jan. 25, 1797; 7 1/2" x 9"; Priestley, Joseph, 1733-1804
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 4p., add. (see his Letters to various persons,no.50) Death of his wife.
  - Letter to John Vaughan, Jan. 21, 1798; 6 1/2" x 8"; Priestley, Joseph, 1733-1804
    Northumberland, A.L.S. 2p. and add. (see his Letters to John Vaughan,no.35) Letters to be forwarded. Mentions Benjamin Vaughan, and the deaths of several persons.
  - Letter to John Vaughan, Sept. 27, 1798; 8" x 9 3/4"; Priestley, Joseph, 1733-1804
    Northumberland, A.L.S. 3p. and add. (see his Letters to John Vaughan,no.36) Mr. Vaughan's difficulties. Finances. Possibility of his son's settling in France.
  - Letter to Dr. [Andrew] Ross, Philadelphia, Dec. 6, 1798; 9-3/4x8; Priestley, Joseph, 1733-1804
    Northumberland, A.L.S. 3p.and add.,end. (see Priestley papers.) Hopes the voyage will help him. Concerning his future plans. Current events in Europe and Egypt.
  - Letter to John Vaughan, Dec. 20, [1798]; 8" x 9 3/4"; Priestley, Joseph, 1733-1804
    A.L. 3p. and add. (see his Letters to John Vaughan,no.37) Packages from London; orders for books, lead, amber, etc. Mentions [William] Cobbett.
  - Letter to John Vaughan, March 21, 1799; 8" x 9 3/4"; Priestley, Joseph, 1733-1804